Gold Protocols, everyone.
‫البروتوكولات الذهبية جميعًا.
Positions. Helipad doors to open.
‫إلى مواقعكم. افتحوا باب مهبط الطائرات.
TARDIS vector one.
‫"تارديس" التوجيه واحد.
Doctor on the bridge.
‫الدكتور في جسر القيادة.
- Give me the lovin'!
‫مرحبًا يا أعزائي!
- Rosa! Rosalinda! Doctor! At last.
‫- "روزا"! "روزاليندا"! ‫- دكتور! أخيرًا.
- It's been so long. - Oh. How is your mum? How's your uncle?
‫- مرت فترة طويلة. ‫- كيف حال أمك وخالك؟
- Yeah, good. - Oh, good. Ruby, Rose. Rose, Ruby.
‫- أجل، بخير. ‫- جيد. هذه "روز" وهذه "روبي".
- Hi. Nice to meet you. - Two different shades of red.
‫- مرحبًا. سُررت بلقائك. ‫- درجتان من الأحمر.
Doctor, welcome aboard.
‫أهلًا بك يا دكتور.
- You're gorgeous. - Thank you.
‫- أنت جميلة. ‫- شكرًا.
Kate.
‫"كيت".
Ruby, this is Kate. We love Kate. I knew Kate's dad. He was the best of men.
‫"روبي"، هذه "كيت". نحب "كيت". ‫كنت أعرف والد "كيت". كان من خيرة الناس.
That is the Vlinx.
‫هذا "فلينكس".
Greetings.
‫تحياتي.
Hot metal, Doctor.
‫فلزات مصهورة يا دكتور.
Colonel Ibrahim.
‫العقيد "إبراهيم".
Someone has been working out.
‫يبدو أنك كنت تتمرن.
- I try. [chuckles] I get busy, you know? Looking good, sir.
‫- أحاول. أشغل نفسي. ‫- تبدو وسيمًا يا سيدي.
Hi. Sorry, I didn't get your name.
‫مرحبًا. آسف، لا أعرف اسمك.
Harriet. Head of the Archive.
‫"هارييت". رئيسة الأرشيف.
Harriet, nice to meet you.
‫"هارييت"، سُررت بلقائك.
And I'm Morris Gibbons, UNIT Scientific Adviser.
‫وأنا "موريس غيبونز"، ‫المستشار العلمي لـ"يونيت".
Thirteen years old, accelerated genius, thanks to a passing asteroid.
‫عبقري معجّل في سن 13 سنة، بفضل كويكب مار.
Thirteen years old.
‫13 سنة.
- Nice to meet you, Morris Gibbons. - Nice to meet you.
‫- سُررت بلقائك يا "موريس غيبونز". ‫- وأنا أيضًا.
- Ruby, this is Morris Gibbons. Hey.
‫- "روبي"، هذا "موريس غيبونز". ‫- مرحبًا.
Nice to meet you, Ruby.
‫سُررت بلقائك يا "روبي".
Okay.
‫حسنًا.
All of you,
‫جميعكم،
I need your help.
‫أحتاج إلى مساعدتكم.
'Cause something really weird keeps happening.
‫لأن شيئًا غريبًا يستمر في الحدوث.
Everywhere I land, a woman appears. Look.
‫تظهر امرأة أينما هبطت. انظروا.
So, she is a comms officer in the planet Pacifico del Rio.
‫إنها ضابطة اتصالات ‫في كوكب "باسيفيكو ديل ريو".
She's someone's mum in Finetime.
‫إنها والدة فتاة في "فاينتايم".
She's an ambulance.
‫إنها إسعاف.
She's a portrait in 1813, and the list goes on.
‫إنها لوحة في 1813، والقائمة تطول.
Planet Sloog, she's a Sloogma. Planet Varsitay, she is a Griffin.
‫إنها "سلوجما" في كوكب "سلوج" ‫و"غريفين" في كوكب "فارسيتاي".
The Fivefold Configuration, she's a Bleet. So she's everywhere.
‫إنها "بليت" في "الترتيب الخماسي". ‫إنها في كل مكان.
She must be here.
‫لا بد أنها هنا.
So I'm hoping that UNIT can find her and analyse her.
‫لذا آمل أنه يمكن لـ"يونيت" ‫العثور عليها وتحليلها.
She's always middle-aged, about so-high, 60, slim, fair hair.
‫إنها دائمًا في أواسط العمر بهذا الارتفاع ‫في سن 60 سنة ونحيلة وبشعر ناعم.
What?
‫ماذا؟
What? What is it?
‫ماذا؟ ما الأمر؟
And right on cue.
‫وفي اللحظة المناسبة.
This is when it changes.
‫حينها يتغير.
This is when the whole world is changed by me.
‫حينها سأغيّر العالم كله.
All right, all right.
‫حسنًا.
- Thank you. - Susan Triad, IT genius.
‫- شكرًا. ‫- "سوزان ترياد". عبقرية تقنية.
And today, she's releasing her software worldwide, free of charge.
‫ستطلق برنامجها اليوم حول العالم مجانًا.
- A gift from S Triad Technology. - ...is greed.
‫- هدية من "س ترياد تيكنولوجي". ‫- …الطمع.
- Oh, man. Don't you see? It's people in power
‫- رباه. ألا ترون؟ ‫- إنهم من في السُلطة
clinging on to all that profit.
‫المتشبثون بكل هذه الأرباح.
It's an anagram.
‫إنها إعادة ترتيب للحروف.
S Triad spells out...
‫"س ترياد" تتحول إلى…
"TARDIS".
‫"(تارديس)"
The name is TARDIS Technology.
‫الاسم هو "تارديس تيكنولوجي".
Well, obviously. Thank you.
‫هذا واضح. شكرًا.
Even I got that.
‫حتى أنا فهمت ذلك.
That is why we've been watching her.
‫لهذا كنا نراقبها.
'Cause it spells TARDIS. We know that, but why?
‫لأن هذه حروف "تارديس". ‫نعرف ذلك، لكن لماذا؟
It's not just that. Never mind the anagram. Look at her name.
‫ليس ذلك فحسب. انس إعادة ترتيب الحروف. ‫انظر إلى اسمها.
Isn't that the point, Doctor?
‫أليس هذا بيت القصيد يا دكتور؟
She's called Susan.
‫إنها تُدعى "سوزان".
Is that significant?
‫هل لهذا أهمية؟
Susan is the name of my granddaughter.
‫"سوزان" اسم حفيدتي.
It is my honour to be here today...
‫يشرفني أن أكون هنا اليوم…
Susan Triad, entrepreneur, genius, philanthropist.
‫"سوزان ترياد"، رائدة أعمال وعبقرية ومحسنة.
She's even been the book at bedtime on CBeebies.
‫إنها حتى ظهرت على "سي بيبيز" ‫لقراءة قصة قبل النوم.
Three years ago, she launched Triad.
‫أنشأت "ترياد" قبل ثلاث سنوات.
It only rebranded as S Triad Technology two months ago,
‫أُعيد تسميتها لـ"س ترياد تيكنولوجي" ‫قبل شهرين فحسب،
and we were straight onto her.
‫وبدأنا نحقق في أمرها منذ ذلك الحين.
Well, even without the TARDIS anagram.
‫حتى من دون إعادة ترتيب حروف "تارديس".
Evil genius with secret alien software, it was top of our list.
‫العباقرة الأشرار ببرامج سرّية فضائية ‫من أهم أولوياتنا.
God knows we've stopped enough of them.
‫أوقفنا الكثيرين منهم بالتأكيد.
Well, except the obvious.
‫باستثناء من هو واضح.
We'll get him.
‫سنقبض عليه.
But the research with Susan has come to nothing.
‫لكن لم نجد شيئًا حين حققنا في أمر "سوزان".
Yeah, and the software's clean. No secret alien signals.
‫أجل والبرنامج آمن. لا تُوجد إشارات فضائية.
Kinda disappointed.
‫شعرت بخيبة أمل.
But hold on. Excuse me. Doctor, am I being thick here?
‫لكن لحظة، المعذرة. ‫هل هذه فكرة غبية مني يا دكتور؟
I mean, don't you recognise her?
‫ألا تميزها؟
Okay.
‫حسنًا.
The truth is, Time Lords can regenerate their faces like a disguise.
‫الحقيقة هي أن أسياد الزمن ‫بوسعهم تجديد وجوههم مثل تنكّر.
So we look different, but we're still the same.
‫لذا نبدو مختلفين لكننا نظل نحن.
Right. [chuckles] Okay.
‫صحيح. حسنًا.
But what for?
‫لكن ما السبب؟
It can save us if we're dying.
‫يمكن لذلك إنقاذنا إن كنا نُحتضر.
...to be able to make a global difference.
‫…لنتمكن من إحداث الاختلاف العالمي.
...with a new face.
‫…بوجه جديد.
And that is what I intend.
‫وهذا ما أنويه.
Does that sound mad?
‫هل يبدو ذلك جنونًا؟
- Triad can make a difference. - Just don't go changing yours, okay?
‫- يمكن لـ"ترياد" تشكيل فرق. ‫- لا تغيّر وجهك فحسب.
Oh, no. I'm keeping this one for a long, long time.
‫لا. سأحتفظ بهذا لوقت طويل.
But is this her actual face, or did she choose it?
‫لكن هل هذا وجهها الحقيقي أم اختارته؟
Name, anagram, TARDIS.
‫الاسم وإعادة ترتيب الحروف و"تارديس".
Probability of a trap, 95% and rising.
‫احتمالية وجود فخ هي 95 بالمئة وترتفع.
Because this is the start of a better future.
‫لأن هذه بداية مستقبل أفضل.
A prosperous future for everyone.
‫مستقبل مزدهر للجميع.
Susan, Susan, Susan, Susan, Susan.
‫"سوزان".
That's a bit mad, isn't it? Chanting my name?
‫أليس الهتاف باسمي جنونًا؟
I'm not Beyoncé.
‫أنا لست "بيونسيه".
Oh, it was just a rehearsal.
‫كانت مجرد بروفة.
We hacked the link.
‫اخترقنا الاتصال. هذا مقر "ترياد" الرئيسي ‫على بُعد كيلومتر ونصف غربًا.
She goes live at 1500 to the whole world.
‫ستظهر في بث مباشر الساعة الـ3 عصرًا ‫أمام العالم كله.
We're not fooling anyone.
‫لن ينخدع أحد بذلك.
The shareholders like it.
‫هذا يعجب المساهمون.
What do you think, Mel?
‫ما رأيك يا "ميل"؟
Well, it got me cheering.
‫جعلني أريد الهتاف.
- Oh, that's Mel! That's my mate Mel.
‫هذه "ميل" صديقتي!
- Oh, you would love Mel. Bonkers.
‫ستحبين "ميل". هذا جنون.
We got her undercover on the media team,
‫جعلناها تعمل متخفية في فريقها الإعلامي،
and she's discovered one surprising thing.
‫واكتشفت أمرًا مفاجئًا.
Susan Triad turns out to be really nice.
‫تبيّن أن "سوزان ترياد" لطيفة حقًا.
I wish we had a real crowd. It's hard to find the right pitch.
‫ليت كان لدينا جمهور حقيقي. ‫يصعب العثور على طبقة الصوت المناسبة.
- Thanks, Mel. - Okay.
‫- شكرًا يا "ميل". ‫- على الرحب.
Am I going to sound all grandiose?
‫هل سأبدو متسمة بالمبالغة؟
No. You sound celebratory.
‫لا. ستبدين محتفلة.
You're giving a gift to the whole planet. You're allowed to enjoy yourself.
‫أنت تمنحين هدية للكوكب بأكمله. ‫مسموح لك بالاستمتاع بما حققته.
It's gonna be brilliant, Susan. I wanted to cheer.
‫سيكون هذا رائعًا يا "سوزان". أردت أن أهتف.
Thank you, Sue.
‫شكرًا يا "سو".
No rest for the wicked.
‫لا وقت للراحة.
- Two hours till the big one. Mm-hmm.
‫أمامنا ساعتان على البث المباشر.
Come on. I wanna rewrite that middle section.
‫هيا. أريد إعادة كتابة القسم الأوسط.
Okay.
‫حسنًا.
So we have Susan Triad.
‫لدينا "سوزان ترياد".
We also have another mystery woman, hmm?
‫ولدينا امرأة غامضة أخرى أيضًا.
- Ruby Sunday! Oh, you could've warned me.
‫- "روبي صنداي"! ‫- كان بوسعك تحذيري.
- That's amazing. You look gorgeous. - Oh, that's my sixteenth.
‫- هذا رائع. تبدين فاتنة. ‫- هذا عيد ميلادي الـ16.
Okay, so Ruby is not the mystery woman, but your mother is.
‫حسنًا، "روبي" ليست المرأة الغامضة، ‫لكنها أمها.
Ruby is a foundling and was left on Ruby Road.
‫"روبي" لقيطة وتُركت في شارع "روبي".
We've got your history, after that incursion on December 24th,
‫حصلنا على ماضيك، ‫بعد ذلك الغزو في الـ24 من ديسمبر،
filed under "goblins".
‫محفوظ في ملف "العفاريت".
- Harriet.
‫"هارييت".
You were quite famous for a day or two.
‫كنت مشهورة ليوم أو يومين.
The Christmas baby.
‫رضيعة الكريسماس.
Oh, yeah. We tried to find my mum, but--
‫أجل. حاولنا العثور على أمي، لكن…
Actually we even tried Davina McCall, but we got nothing.
‫جرّبنا حتى "دافينا ماكول" ‫لكننا لم نعثر على شيء.
Ah, I love Davina.
‫أُحب "دافينا".
- I love Davina. Is she nice?
‫أنا أُحب "دافينا". أهي لطيفة؟
She's absolutely lovely.
‫إنها في غاية اللطف.
That's one good thing.
‫هذا أمر جيد.
So-- Sorry. You've got, uh, a woman that you keep seeing
‫المعذرة. ثمة امرأة تراها باستمرار
and a woman that you've never seen.
‫وامرأة لم ترها قط.
Is it the same woman?
‫أهي المرأة نفسها؟
Susan Triad would've been 40, 42, and women who abandon their children
‫كانت سن "سوزان ترياد" حينها ‫لتكون 40 أو 42 سنة ومن يهجرن أطفالهن
tend to be teenagers or early 20s, statistically.
‫يكنّ مراهقات أو في أول العشرينيات إحصائيًا.
Sorry, but can I say the obvious?
‫المعذرة، لكن أيمكنني قول ما هو واضح؟
You've got a time machine. Doctor, can't you just go back and take a look?
‫تملك آلة زمن يا دكتور، ‫ألا يمكنك العودة وإلقاء نظرة؟
No. No. I can't.
‫لا يمكنني ذلك.
I've been to Ruby Road once, and I can't cross over my own history.
‫زرت شارع "روبي" مرة، ‫ولا يمكنني التقاطع مع ماضيّ.
The one night that we need to see, and I have time-locked myself out of it.
‫الليلة الوحيدة التي نحتاج إلى رؤيتها، ‫واحتجزت نفسي زمنيًا خارجها.
That's not like you. You love to break the rules.
‫هذا ليس من شيمك. تحب خرق القواعد.
Yeah, but...
‫أجل، لكن…
it snows.
‫هطلت الثلوج.
It snows?
‫هطلت الثلوج؟
Oh, it really snows.
‫هطلت الثلوج كثيرًا.
It was snowing the night that Ruby was born,
‫كانت الثلوج تهطل ليلة مولد "روبي"
and it keeps snowing all around her.
‫وواصلت الهطول حولها.
Actual snow, which means that that night is so raw and so open,
‫ثلج حقيقي، ما يعني أن تلك الليلة ‫كانت غير متغيرة ومفتوحة،
the last thing that I should do is take a time machine back there.
‫وآخر ما أريد فعله ‫هو العودة إلى هناك بآلة زمن.
Excuse me. It all sounds a bit Dickensian with the baby
‫المعذرة. يبدو هذا كله ‫كأنه من روايات "تشارلز ديكنز" بالرضيعة
and the church and the snow, but it was 2004.
‫والكنيسة والثلج، لكنها كانت سنة 2004.
There was CCTV footage.
‫كانت هناك لقطات كاميرا مراقبة.
The camera was positioned in a storage yard 66 metres away.
‫وُضعت الكاميرا في فناء تخزين ‫على بُعد 66 مترًا.
But does it show anything? Does the tape still exist?
‫لكن هل أظهرت شيئًا؟ هل ما زال للشريط وجود؟
Oh, no, no. We've got it. Yeah, my gran asked for it,
‫لا. حصلنا عليه. أجل، طلبته جدتي،
'cause it's mine, and it's all I've got, but you can't see anything.
‫لأنه لي وهو كل ما أملكه، ‫لكن لا يمكن رؤية شيء.
It's black and white, and snow at midnight--
‫الصورة أسود وأبيض ‫ويهطل ثلج في منتصف الليل…
Yeah. Yeah, but look at our technology.
‫أجل. لكن انظري إلى تقنيتنا.
We can sharpen the image.
‫بوسعنا تحسين الصورة.
Oh, my God.
‫يا إلهي.
Do you think you can clean it up? I can see my mother.
‫هل بوسعكم تحسينها؟ سيمكنني رؤية أمي.
My mum's got it. She's got it in a box.
‫تحتفظ أمي به في صندوق.
I suggest we take Miss Sunday home.
‫أقترح أن نأخذ الآنسة "صنداي" إلى منزلها.
- At once, ma'am.
‫في الحال يا سيدتي.
- This way. - Thank you.
‫- من هنا. ‫- شكرًا.
Oh. I'm coming too.
‫سأذهب أيضًا.
They never give me proper work.
‫لا يعطونني عملًا لائقًا أبدًا.
They have me investigating shoplifting in Catford.
‫جعلوني أحقق في سرقة معروضات في "كاتفورد".
"I want Triad to be in every home.
‫"أريد أن يكون (ترياد) في كل بيت.
At the heart of every family, 365 days a year."
‫وفي وسط كل عائلة، طوال أيام السنة."
I took out that bit about coals to Newcastle.
‫حذفت الجزء الخاص ‫بمثل بيع الفحم في "نيوكاسل".
- Hmm. - Doesn't really work in China.
‫لن يُفهم في "الصين".
Hi. Don't wanna interrupt. I got those figures from Hanya.
‫مرحبًا. لا أريد المقاطعة. ‫حصلت على تلك الأرقام من "هانيا".
She is so happy. I have never seen anyone smile so much.
‫إنها سعيدة جدًا. ‫لم أر أحدًا يبتسم بذلك القدر قط.
- Oh, just terrified, that's all. - You'll be amazing.
‫- أنا مرتعبة، هذا كل شيء. ‫- ستكونين مذهلة.
I don't know how you think of all this stuff.
‫- لا أعرف كيف تفكرين في كل تلك الأمور. ‫- تعلمت هذا من أمي وأبي.
I mean, we didn't have much. He was a postman. She was a dinner lady.
‫لم نملك الكثير. ‫كان ساعي بريد وكانت طباخة في مدرسة.
But they told me, "You can do anything."
‫لكنهما قالا لي، "بوسعك فعل أي شيء."
And look at me now.
‫وانظرا إليّ الآن.
Ninety minutes' time, I address the United Nations.
‫سأخاطب "الأمم المتحدة" خلال 90 دقيقة.
Here it is. Safe and sound.
‫ها هو ذا. آمن وسليم.
That's your story, darling.
‫يحتوي على قصتك يا عزيزتي.
The legend of Ruby Sunday.
‫أسطورة "روبي صنداي".
But they can analyse it.
‫لكن بوسعهم تحليله.
Maybe we can see my birth mother. If we can see her face just once.
‫ربما بوسعنا رؤية أمي البيولوجية. ‫إن استطعنا رؤية وجهها لمرة.
They've got amazing technology.
‫يملكون تقنية مذهلة.
I mean, it can do anything.
‫بوسعها فعل أي شيء.
You work for UNIT?
‫هل تعملين لدى "يونيت"؟
My mother's part of it.
‫أمي جزء منها.
Is she?
‫حقًا؟
Well, if your mother's part of it,
‫إن كانت أمك جزءًا منها،
then, Ruby, you can tell her your mother is too.
‫فبوسعك إخبارها يا "روبي" ‫بأن أمك جزء منها أيضًا.
Now go and get Mrs Flood.
‫اذهبي وأحضري السيدة "فلود".
- What for? - Go and get her!
‫- لماذا؟ ‫- أحضريها!
Vamoose! 'Cause I'm coming with you to the nitwit tower!
‫أسرعي! لأنني سأرافقك إلى ذلك البرج السخيف!
There's a warning of thunderstorms across...
‫ثمة تحذير لعواصف برقية عبر…
Anything I can do to help.
‫سأفعل أي شيء للمساعدة.
Uh, it's nice for me to get out.
‫من اللطيف أن أخرج من المنزل.
I'm always hiding myself away.
‫أخفي نفسي دائمًا.
I just need you to look after Mum. It's only gonna be for a couple of hours.
‫أريدك أن ترعي أمي فحسب. ‫سأتغيّب لبضع ساعات.
Oh, leave her to me.
‫دعي الأمر لي.
I nursed my old mum through diabetes and a hip operation.
‫رعيت أمي عند إصابتها بالسكّري وجراحة وركها.
She died of an ulcer.
‫ماتت بالقرحة.
But that was when I wasn't looking.
‫لكن لم يحدث ذلك في أثناء رعايتي لها.
Aren't you a beauty?
‫أنت جميلة.
- Thank you.
‫شكرًا.
You too, Ruby.
‫وأنت أيضًا يا "روبي".
Mum, I'm leaving you with Mrs Flood.
‫سأتركك مع السيدة "فلود" يا أمي.
You've got your pills. Two yellow tablets at five o'clock.
‫لديك أقراصك. ‫قرصان أصفران في الساعة الـ5 مساءً.
If you're chasing after that Doctor man, I'm warning you. Him is trouble.
‫إن كنت تلاحقين ذلك الدكتور، ‫فأنا أحذرك. إنه مصدر متاعب.
Everything is trouble.
‫كل شيء مصدر متاعب.
And I've decided it's about time I cause trouble for myself.
‫وقررت أن الوقت قد حان لأسبب المتاعب بنفسي.
Thank you, Mrs F.
‫شكرًا يا سيدة "ف".
Come on, girls. Let's find that woman.
‫هيا يا فتاتان. لنعثر على تلك المرأة.
I would love a cup of tea.
‫أودّ احتساء كوب شاي.
Would you, sweetheart?
‫حقًا يا عزيزتي؟
Well, we'd all like a lot of things that aren't going to happen.
‫جميعنا نودّ أمورًا كثيرة لن تحدث أبدًا.
What that supposed to mean?
‫ما معنى ذلك؟
I'd be very careful, Mrs Sunday.
‫لو كنت مكانك لتوخيت الحذر يا سيدة "صنداي".
There's a storm coming in.
‫ثمة عاصفة تقترب.
He waits no more.
‫انتهى انتظاره.
My father, he'd tell me stories about you when I was a kid.
‫أخبرني أبي بقصص عنك حين كنت طفلة.
telling tales of the Doctor, his eyes shining.
‫ويحكي قصصًا عن الدكتور وعيناه تلمعان.
But he never ever mentioned a granddaughter.
‫لكنه لم يذكر وجود حفيدة قط.
I was a different Doctor back then, Kate.
‫كنت دكتورًا مختلفًا حينها يا "كيت".
Still can't shake it off. I'm trying.
‫ما زلت لا أتأقلم مع ذلك. لكنني أحاول.
If you've got a granddaughter, that means you've got kids.
‫إن كانت لديك حفيدة، ‫فهذا يعني أن لديك أطفالًا.
Well, not quite.
‫ليس بالضبط.
Not yet.
‫ليس بعد.
But-- You mean you can have a granddaughter before a daughter?
‫أتعني أن بوسعك أن تحظى بحفيدة ‫قبل أن تحظى بابنة؟
Life of a Time Lord.
‫إنها حياة سيد زمن.
But--
‫لكن…
Okay.
‫حسنًا.
The grandchild exists, and you've got the TARDIS,
‫الحفيدة موجودة، ولديك "تارديس"،
but you've never gone back to see her. Why not?
‫لكنك لم تعد لرؤيتها قط. لم لا؟
You've seen my life.
‫أنت رأيت حياتي.
I bring disaster, Kate.
‫أجلب المصائب يا "كيت".
- Disaster.
‫مصائب.
What if I go back and ruin her?
‫ماذا إن عُدت في الزمن وأفسدت حياتها؟
For what it's worth, I think you bring joy.
‫إن كان لرأيي قيمة، أظن أنك تجلب البهجة.
Do you think Susan Triad is her?
‫هل تظن أن "سوزان ترياد" حفيدتك؟
Do you want it to be?
‫هل تريدها أن تكون حفيدتك؟
Doctor, what if you just said hello?
‫دكتور، ما رأيك أن تلقي التحية فحسب؟
To her face.
‫وجهًا لوجه.
Look her in the eye. Would you recognise her?
‫هل ستتعرف عليها إن نظرت إلى عينيها؟
Yes.
‫أجل.
Yes, but S Triad Technology, the anagram...
‫أجل، لكن "س ترياد تيكنولوجي"، ‫إعادة تبديل الحروف…
Like Morris said, probability of a trap, 95%.
‫كما قال "موريس"، ‫احتمالية وجود فخ 95 بالمئة.
- Ninety-six. - Ninety--
‫- 96. ‫- 96…
You see? I can't.
‫أترين؟ لا أستطيع.
Come here. Come on.
‫اقترب. هيا.
I'll have some of that.
‫أريد المشاركة في هذا العناق.
- Oh! - Oh, yes!
‫رائع!
- Hello, trouble.
‫مرحبًا يا مثيرة المتاعب.
Come on, you two.
‫تعاليا.
In 65 minutes, it's 1500 UK time.
‫خلال 65 دقيقة، الساعة الـ3 عصرًا ‫بتوقيت "المملكة المتحدة".
10:00 a.m. in the USA.
‫الـ10 صباحًا في "أمريكا".
That's when Susan Triad addresses the United Nations.
‫ستخاطب "سوزان ترياد" "الأمم المتحدة".
And I've got my daily DNA sample which says that Susan Triad is...
‫وحصلت على عيّنة الحمض النووي اليومية ‫والتي تشير إلى أن "سوزان ترياد"…
Susan Triad. Human confirmed.
‫"سوزان ترياد". بشرية بشكل مؤكد.
- But we know that already, don't we? - Mmm.
‫لكننا نعرف هذا بالفعل.
Kate's got a chrysalis theory.
‫تفكر "كيت" في نظرية الخادرة.
Uh, just because Susan Triad is nice doesn't mean she can't change.
‫لمجرد أن "سوزان ترياد" لطيفة، ‫فهذا لا يعني أنه لا يسعها أن تتغير.
A caterpillar doesn't know it's a butterfly.
‫لا تعرف اليرقة أنها فراشة.
And a phoenix is just a bird until it burns.
‫والعنقاء مجرد طائر حتى يحترق.
I got it! I got it, I got it, I got it!
‫أحضرته!
But they stuck Mum in a room downstairs. They won't let her in.
‫لكنهم احتجزوا أمي في الأسفل. ‫لن يسمحوا لها بالدخول.
Ruby, this is a Gold Security establishment.
‫"روبي"، هذه منشأة بمستوى الأمن الذهبي.
Even the prime minister can't walk into UNIT.
‫حتى رئيس الوزراء لا يمكنه دخول "يونيت".
Especially the prime minister.
‫خاصةً رئيس الوزراء.
Yeah, but it's Carla. Come on.
‫أجل، لكنها "كارلا". بحقكم.
Carla Sunday. Access granted.
‫"كارلا صنداي". سُمح لها بالدخول.
Right. Fine. Thanks.
‫صحيح. لا بأس. شكرًا.
Hey. And this.
‫وهذا.
This is the key!
‫هذا مفتاح حلّ اللغز!
Kate, do you have a Time Window?
‫"كيت"، هل لديك نافذة زمنية؟
Wh-- You expressly told us in the 1970s,
‫أمرتنا بوضوح في السبعينيات،
UNIT was absolutely forbidden to experiment with
‫بأنه يُحظر على "يونيت" أن تختبر
any form of time technology.
‫أي نوع من تقنيات الزمن.
- Do you have a Time Window? - Ten floors down.
‫- هل لديك نافذة زمنية؟ ‫- 10 طوابق في الأسفل.
Time Window open.
‫فُتحت النافذة الزمنية.
Membrane steady at 5000 chronons in n-dimensional time, and holding.
‫الغشاء مستقر عند 5 آلاف كرونون ‫في الزمن متغيّر الأبعاد، وثابت.
Relative temporal distortion standing at -0.1 seconds.
‫الانحراف الزمني النسبي ‫ثابت عند سالب 0.1 ثانية.
This is-- This is rough.
‫إنها بدائية.
Wow. You have lashed this together.
‫عجبًا. جمعتم كل هذه الأجزاء معًا.
Ouch. Kate.
‫"كيت".
Doctor, this is Colonel Winston Chidozie, head of Time Window Security.
‫دكتور، هذا العقيد "وينستون تشيدوزي"، ‫رئيس أمن النافذة الزمنية.
An honour to work with you, sir. I've heard so much about ya.
‫يُشرّفني العمل معك يا سيدي. سمعت الكثير عنك.
'Ey, is that a Manchester accent?
‫هل هذه لكنة "مانشستر"؟
- Proud to say, ma'am. Cheetham Hill. - Oh, I'm Ruby. I'm from Tameside.
‫- أنا فخور بذلك يا سيدتي. من "تشيتام هيل". ‫- أنا "روبي"، من "تيمسايد".
- Good to meet you, ma'am.
‫يسرّني لقاؤك يا سيدتي.
So-- So, this room charges up using the entire nuclear output of Europe
‫تُشحن هذه الغرفة ‫بناتج طاقة "أوروبا" النووية بأكمله
and projects an image from the past, like 3D history?
‫وتعرض صورة من الماضي، ‫مثل التاريخ ثلاثي الأبعاد؟
Well, we-we get glimpses.
‫نتلقى لمحات.
Little, fleeting moments.
‫لحظات قصيرة وعابرة.
We saw the signing of the Declaration of Independence,
‫رأينا توقيع وثيقة إعلان الاستقلال،
but all I could tell you was the colour of the quill.
‫لكن لا يسعني إلا إخبارك بلون الريشة.
Which was white.
‫كانت بيضاء.
We've got extra power.
‫لدينا طاقة إضافية.
We can feed the Time Window using massive information from the VHS.
‫بوسعنا تغذية النافذة الزمنية ‫باستخدام معلومات هائلة من شريط الفيديو.
Actual positions of the snowflakes.
‫المواقع الحقيقية لندفات الثلج.
Morris Gibbons?
‫"موريس غيبونز"؟
Yes, Doc?
‫أجل يا دكتور؟
Get this VHS wired up to that system,
‫أوصل هذا الشريط بذلك النظام،
because we are going to recreate Christmas Eve 2004.
‫لأننا سنعيد تشكيل عشية الكريسماس ‫لسنة 2004.
Come on!
‫هيا!
There it is.
‫ها هي ذي.
The legend.
‫الأسطورة.
Me and my mum watch it every Christmas Eve.
‫أنا وأمي نشاهده في كل عشية كريسماس.
Like a little sort of ritual. But you can't see anything.
‫كأنه طقس لنا. لكننا لا نرى شيئًا.
The CCTV wasn't even pointing at the church.
‫لم تكن كاميرا المراقبة ‫موجهة إلى الكنيسة حتى.
No, but the information exists.
‫لا، لكن المعلومات موجودة.
We can see that snowflakes fell on a south-east axis,
‫بوسعنا رؤية أن ندفات الثلج تساقطت ‫بمحور جنوب شرقي،
so we can model that onto the church and predict backwards.
‫لذا بوسعنا تمثيل ذلك على الكنيسة ‫والتوقّع بشكل عكسي.
Oh, my God. Mum!
‫رباه. أمي!
How much did it all cost?
‫كم كلّف كل ذلك؟
Hey. All good.
‫مرحبًا. كل شيء بخير.
Right. This might get noisy.
‫صحيح. قد يصير المكان صاخبًا.
Direct all comms traffic through me.
‫وجّهوا كل الاتصالات إليّ.
Now, stay back!
‫تراجعوا!
Behind the glass.
‫قفوا خلف الزجاج.
Everyone, keep the chamber clear.
‫أبقوا الحجرة خاوية.
We are going to rock through time.
‫سنسافر عبر الزمن.
I don't wanna lose anyone.
‫لا أريد أن أفقد أحدًا.
Ruby!
‫"روبي"!
Look after her.
‫اعتني بها.
Don't worry. She's safe.
‫لا تقلقي. إنها في أمان.
I lost my family to the most terrible things.
‫فقدت عائلتي لأسوأ الأشياء.
I swear. Come on.
‫أعدك بذلك. هيا.
- Colonel Chidozie, on guard. Ma'am.
‫- أنت في الحراسة يا عقيد "تشيدوزي". ‫- سيدتي.
Close the Time Window.
‫إغلاق النافذة الزمنية.
Time Window closing.
‫النافذة الزمنية تُغلق.
Time membrane sealed.
‫أُوصد الغشاء الزمني.
Security at Gold Alert.
‫الأمن في مستوى الاستنفار الذهبي.
Now tell me when you were born.
‫أخبريني الآن متى وُلدت.
December 24th... [sighs] ...2004.
‫24 ديسمبر 2004.
You were born on Christmas Eve.
‫وُلدت عشية الكريسماس.
My mother must have been so alone.
‫لا بد أن أمي كانت وحدها تمامًا.
She left me at the church on Ruby Road.
‫تركتني أمام الكنيسة في شارع "روبي".
- And what else? - It was snowing.
‫- وماذا أيضًا؟ ‫- كانت الثلوج تهطل.
- It's snow. - That's impossible.
‫- الثلوج تهطل. ‫- هذا مستحيل.
I'll tell you what's impossible.
‫سأخبرك ما المستحيل.
We haven't turned it on yet.
‫لم نشغّلها بعد.
- Now, I warn you...
‫سأحذرك الآن،
...that time has tides and hollows.
‫للزمن مدّ وجزر وفجوات.
And secrets.
‫وأسرار.
And this fixed point on Christmas Eve is the wildest I have ever seen.
‫وتلك النقطة المحددة في عشية الكريسماس ‫هي أكثر اللحظات التي رأيتها جموحًا.
- Now turn on your machine!
‫شغّلوا الآلة الآن!
Warning. Chronon deteriorating.
‫تحذير. تدهور الكرونون.
- December the 24th. Bring it back! - Bring it back!
‫- لنُعد 24 ديسمبر! ‫- لنُعده!
Bring it back!
‫لنُعده!
- It's Ruby Road. - In 2004.
‫- إنه شارع "روبي". ‫- في 2004.
We did it! We brought it back!
‫فعلناها! أعدناه!
- Oh. Morris, keep it steady. Uh, yep. Uh, I'm trying.
‫- "موريس"، أبقها ثابتة. ‫- أجل. أحاول.
This thing is running way beyond maximum.
‫هذه الآلة تعمل بما يفوق طاقتها.
- Should we stop? - No way.
‫- هل نتوقف؟ ‫- مستحيل.
Hey, listen. Listen.
‫أصغوا.
We've got sound and vision.
‫لدينا صوت وصورة.
I've never seen the Window this strong.
‫لم أر النافذة بتلك القوة قط.
We have given it the greatest power of all.
‫أعطيناها أعظم قوة على الإطلاق.
Memory. Time is remembered. Memory is time.
‫ذكرى. الزمن يُتذكر. الذكرى هي الزمن.
But what happened?
‫لكن ماذا حدث؟
What happened on that night?
‫ماذا حدث في تلك الليلة؟
The woman.
‫المرأة.
She went to the church.
‫ذهبت إلى الكنيسة.
She left Ruby in the doorway.
‫وتركت "روبي" أمام المدخل.
And then she walked away.
‫ورحلت.
Towards us.
‫نحونا.
There she is.
‫ها هي ذي.
Oh, my God.
‫يا إلهي.
That is-is more than just a glitch.
‫هذا أكثر من مجرد خلل فني.
It's like she's shadowed.
‫كأنها تُظلل.
- Mum? - You-You can't move.
‫- أمي؟ ‫- لا يمكنك التحرك.
She's my mum. Can she see us?
‫إنها أمي. أيمكنها رؤيتنا؟
I don't think she can, but you can't move. You can't.
‫لا أظن أنها ترانا، لكن لا يمكنك التحرك.
You gotta keep everything exactly as it was,
‫عليك إبقاء كل شيء كما كان بالضبط،
but she's gonna walk by. Look at her face.
‫لكنها ستمر بنا. انظري إلى وجهها.
Look. Look, look, look. Here she comes.
‫انظري. ها هي قادمة.
- No! - Ruby, please. Ruby, please. Morris!
‫- لا! ‫- "روبي"، أرجوك. "موريس"!
Chronon surge. - Morris, what is happening?
‫- تدفق فائق للكرونون. ‫- "موريس"، ماذا يحدث؟
- Power vents flooding like crazy. - Chronon surge.
‫- تتدفق الطاقة من الفتحات. ‫- تدفق فائق للكرونون.
- I want to see her! Ruby, don't move.
‫- أريد أن أراها! ‫- لا تتحركي يا "روبي".
We need to keep the image fixed.
‫علينا إبقاء الصورة ثابتة.
Did anyone see her face?
‫هل رأى أحد وجهها؟
- No. Nothing. - Nothing. Sorry.
‫- لا. لا شيء. ‫- لا شيء. آسفة.
Colonel Chidozie?
‫العقيد "تشيدوزي"؟
Can't make her out. Sorry, Doctor.
‫لا أميّز ملامحها. آسف يا دكتور.
Why?
‫لماذا؟
What is so different about her?
‫ما المختلف بشأنها؟
I am arriving.
‫وصلت.
That's me.
‫هذا أنا.
The original me.
‫نسختي الأصلية.
Coming back in time in 2004 because goblins.
‫عُدت إلى 2004 بسبب العفاريت.
But I had to go back to the church to save little baby Ruby.
‫لكن كان عليّ العودة إلى الكنيسة ‫لإنقاذ "روبي" الرضيعة.
That TARDIS is almost solid.
‫تكاد "تارديس" تلك أن تكون صلبة.
If time is memory and memory is time, then what is the memory of a time machine?
‫إن كان الزمن ذكرى والذكرى زمن، ‫فماذا تكون ذكرى آلة زمن؟
Oh, look. Look, look. She's still there.
‫انظري. ما زالت هناك.
What is she doing? Can you see? Why did she stop?
‫ماذا تفعل؟ هل ترين؟ لماذا توقفت؟
Did she see me fighting?
‫هل رأتني أقاتل؟
Anyone? Can you see?
‫أيمكن لأحد أن يرى؟
Doctor, I think she's crying.
‫دكتور، أظن أنها تبكي.
She's crying her heart out.
‫تبكي بشدة.
I took her in, darling.
‫اعتنيت بها يا عزيزتي.
And she's safe.
‫وهي في أمان.
And she's wonderful.
‫وهي مدهشة.
I wish I could tell her. I made it, Mum.
‫ليتني أُخبرها. نجوت يا أمي.
You should see what I've done. I-I travelled the universe.
‫يجب أن تري ما فعلته. سافرت في أنحاء الكون.
And I, uh-- I came back, running.
‫وعُدت راكضًا.
And that's when I saw the woman.
‫وحينها رأيت المرأة.
My memory of this keeps changing, like,
‫تواصل ذاكرتي عن هذا في التغيّر،
time keeps changing.
‫كأن الزمن يواصل التغيّر.
She's pointing at ya.
‫إنها تشير إليك.
Uh, can she see you? Did my mother see you?
‫أيمكنها رؤيتك؟ هل رأتك أمي؟
I don't know why she was pointing at me.
‫لا أعرف لماذا تشير إليّ.
There's nothing behind you, Doctor.
‫لا شيء خلفك يا دكتور.
Anything? Anyone?
‫هل يرى أحدكم شيئًا؟
Does she know who you are?
‫هل تعرف من تكون؟
Morris, can-can you magnify the woman?
‫"موريس"، أيمكنك تكبير صورة المرأة؟
My hands are on fire here.
‫أعمل بأقصى سرعة.
She's pointing at you, but she's also pointing north-west.
‫تشير إليك، ‫لكنها تشير إلى الشمال الغربي أيضًا.
Is there anything there?
‫هل ثمة أي شيء هناك؟
Colonel Chidozie, you will return to your position.
‫العقيد "تشيدوزي"، عُد إلى موقعك.
Just see if there's anything there.
‫سيرى فحسب إن كان هناك شيء.
- Doctor, you said not to move. - I know. I know.
‫- دكتور، طلبت ألّا يتحرك أحد. ‫- أعرف.
But just-- just look.
‫لكن انظر فحسب.
Proceeding forward, ma'am.
‫أتقدّم يا سيدتي.
There's nothing.
‫لا يُوجد شيء.
There's just the lamp post and--
‫مجرد عمود الإنارة و…
And all I've got is trees and stuff.
‫وكل ما أراه هو أشجار وما شابه.
Houses in the distance. Nothing.
‫ثمة منازل في الأفق. لا شيء.
Maybe if I try a different angle.
‫ربما إن جرّبت زاوية مختلفة.
Colonel, be careful!
‫احذر أيها العقيد!
No. Sorry. No.
‫لا. آسف.
Not even a flicker.
‫لا يُوجد بصيص ضوء حتى.
- I've got nothing, Doctor.
‫لا أرى شيئًا يا دكتور.
Why was she pointing at me?
‫لماذا كانت تشير إليّ؟
Doctor! She's walking away.
‫دكتور! إنها ترحل.
- No, don't. No, Mum, please don't-- - Ruby, Ruby.
‫- لا ترحلي يا أمي أرجوك. ‫- "روبي".
Please don't--
‫أرجوك لا…
And then I just turned away.
‫ثم استدرت.
I can't see her.
‫لا أستطيع رؤيتها.
Doctor, can I ask?
‫دكتور، أيمكنني السؤال؟
What is that?
‫ما ذلك؟
Doctor.
‫دكتور.
Doctor, what is that thing?
‫دكتور، ما هذا الشيء؟
- Where's Colonel Chidozie? - At arms!
‫- أين العقيد "تشيدوزي"؟ ‫- أشهروا أسلحتكم!
Don't go into the Window. - No. No! No.
‫- لا تدخل إلى النافذة. ‫- لا!
Stay where you are!
‫ابق حيث أنت!
Chidozie?
‫"تشيدوزي"؟
Where are you? Are you in there?
‫أين أنت؟ هل أنت في الداخل؟
Winston, are you in that shape?
‫"وينستون"، هل أنت في هذا الشكل؟
Colonel Chidozie, you will report at once. Can you hear me?
‫العقيد "تشيدوزي"، تحدّث حالًا. هل تسمعني؟
Is-Is it now or is it 2004?
‫أهو الآن أم في 2004؟
- I don't know. - What is it though?
‫- لا أعرف. ‫- لكن ماذا يكون؟
- Has it come for my mother? - I don't know.
‫- هل جاء من أجل أمي؟ ‫- لا أعرف.
- Is it us? Has it come for us? I don't know.
‫- هل جاء من أجلنا؟
Colonel Chidozie, please report.
‫العقيد "تشيدوزي"، تحدّث رجاءً.
Warning.
‫- تحذير. تصاعد الكرونون. ‫- تخطت المقاييس.
- That thing is hot. It's cold. - Warning.
‫- هذا الشيء ساخن وبارد. ‫- تحذير.
It's radioactive. It's dead. It's everything. I don't know.
‫إنه مشعّ وميت وكل شيء. لا أعرف.
I know its name.
‫أعرف اسمه.
It's the Beast.
‫إنه "الوحش".
Winston.
‫"وينستون".
Winston, where are you? Are you still in this room?
‫"وينستون"، أين أنت؟ هل ما زلت في الغرفة؟
Colonel Chidozie, please report.
‫العقيد "تشيدوزي"، الرجاء التحدث.
Where are you, Cheetham Hill?
‫أين أنت يا "تشيتام هيل"؟
Cheetham Hill. - That-That-- That's him.
‫- "تشيتام هيل". ‫- هذا هو.
He's alive.
‫إنه حي.
Hey, soldier. I'm still here. Tameside girl.
‫أيها الجندي. ‫أنا فتاة "تيمسايد" ما زلت هنا.
We're trying to see--
‫نحاول أن نرى…
Are you inside that thing?
‫هل أنت داخل هذا الشيء؟
No.
‫لا.
Then where are ya?
‫أين أنت إذًا؟
I am lost.
‫أنا تائه.
Okay, but we can find you. We can help.
‫حسنًا، لكن بوسعنا العثور عليك ومساعدتك.
Just look around and tell us. Where are ya?
‫انظر حولك وأخبرنا بمكانك.
I am in hell.
‫أنا في الجحيم.
Colonel, I need to know.
‫يجب أن أعرف أيها العقيد.
Can you tell us what's happening?
‫أيمكنك إخبارنا بما يحدث؟
It's seen me.
‫رآني.
It's seen right into my soul.
‫رأى إلى داخل روحي.
And it's so old.
‫إنه قديم جدًا.
What is it?
‫ما هو؟
Waiting. What is?
‫- ينتظر. ‫- ما هو؟
It's been waiting for so long.
‫كان ينتظر منذ وقت طويل.
Open the doors.
‫افتح الباب.
Keep back. Everyone, keep back.
‫تراجعوا جميعًا.
He looks like he's been dead for a hundred years.
‫يبدو كأنه مات منذ مئة سنة.
I'm so sorry.
‫أنا آسف جدًا.
- This is the commander-in-chief
‫أنا القائدة العامة ‫إلى فريق الحذف التنفيذي.
We have an officer down. Colonel Winston Lemuel Chidozie.
‫سقط ضابط. العقيد "وينستون ليميول تشيدوزي".
Floor 45. I want Psych Ops informed.
‫الطابق 45. ‫أريد إبلاغ قسم العمليات النفسية.
I want UNIT forensics.
‫أريد قسم الطب الشرعي في "يونيت".
I want full Option 10 and 11 Schematics.
‫أريد المخططين 10 و11 بكل الخيارات.
- Immediately. Yes, ma'am.
‫- في الحال. ‫- حسنًا يا سيدتي.
Mel.
‫"ميل".
Take me to Susan Triad.
‫خذيني إلى "سوزان ترياد".
She's due to make the speech at three o'clock.
‫ستلقي خطابًا الساعة الـ3 عصرًا.
We've got ten minutes.
‫أمامنا 10 دقائق.
I'm with the media team. Thanks.
‫أنا في فريق الإعلام. شكرًا.
I sent him forward.
‫أمرته بالتقدم.
That thing killed him.
‫قتله ذلك الشيء.
- Not you. - What was it?
‫- وليس أنت. ‫- ما كان ذلك؟
And Ruby's mother, why was she pointing at me?
‫ووالدة "روبي"، لماذا كانت تشير إليّ؟
Finished?
‫هل انتهيت؟
Now stop grizzling and fix it.
‫توقّف عن البكاء وأصلح الأمر الآن.
'Cause if Susan is your granddaughter, then she might be the key to this.
‫لأن إن كانت "سوزان" حفيدتك، ‫فربما تكون الحل لكل هذا.
Now come on.
‫هيا.
Doctor, we've isolated an image.
‫عزلنا صورة يا دكتور.
Whatever that thing was, it burnt itself out of the Time Window.
‫أيًا كان ذلك الشيء، ‫فقد اختفى من النافذة الزمنية.
But it survived on the VHS.
‫لكنه نجا على شريط الفيديو.
That wasn't there before. I swear to ya.
‫لم يكن هناك من قبل. أقسم لكم.
Every time I've watched that tape, it wasn't there.
‫لم يكن هناك في كل مرة شاهدت الشريط.
- The recording has changed. Kate, analyse it.
‫- تغيّر التسجيل. ‫- حلليه يا "كيت".
Break it down. Every single pixel.
‫افحصي كل البكسلات.
We need to know what that thing is. I need to see.
‫يجب أن نعرف ما ذلك الشيء. أحتاج إلى رؤيته.
I've got image control.
‫أتولّى التحكم في الصورة.
All desks link to mine.
‫كل الحواسيب مربوطة بحاسوبي.
- Coordinating now.
‫أنسّق الآن.
What do you think?
‫ما رأيك؟
It's a crude videotape of a snowstorm.
‫إنه شريط فيديو غير محسّن لعاصفة ثلجية.
Nineteen years old. Kept under the bed in a shoebox.
‫عمره 19 سنة وحُفظ في علبة حذاء تحت الفراش.
I was born for this.
‫وُلدت لفعل هذا.
Susan, could I introduce my friend?
‫"سوزان"، أيمكنني أن أعرّفك بصديقي؟
- Not right now. We're about to go on. - Hello. Hi there.
‫- ليس الآن. نحن على وشك البث. ‫- مرحبًا.
- I'm the Doctor. - Ah, nice to meet you, pet.
‫- أنا الدكتور. ‫- سُررت بلقائك يا عزيزي.
- Doctor who? - Just the Doctor. Hello.
‫- دكتور من؟ ‫- الدكتور فحسب. مرحبًا.
Well, top marks for enigmatic.
‫أنت غامض جدًا.
Yeah. Yeah.
‫أجل.
Have we met before?
‫هل التقينا من قبل؟
- Well, I don't think so. - Are you sure?
‫- لا أظن ذلك. ‫- هل أنت متأكدة؟
Well, if you don't mind my saying, I'd remember a handsome chap like you.
‫إن لم تمانع قولي ذلك، ‫كنت لأتذكّر رجلًا بوسامتك.
It's just that I thought you were...
‫ظننت أنك…
- We're on in 60 seconds. - But, Susan, I need to talk to you.
‫- سيبدأ البث خلال 60 ثانية. ‫- لكن يجب أن أتحدّث إليك يا "سوزان".
- Just for a couple of minutes. - If you could tell your friend.
‫- لدقيقتين فحسب. ‫- أخبري صديقك.
Look, a lot of people want my time.
‫يريد الكثيرون بعضًا من وقتي.
All I want is a bit of shut-eye.
‫وكل ما أريده هو بعض النوم.
- God knows I don't get enough sleep. - Why not?
‫- لا أنام بما يكفي. ‫- لم لا؟
I get a lot of dreams.
‫تراودني أحلام كثيرة.
What do you dream about?
‫ماذا ترين في أحلامك؟
I'm sorry, but we're going to be late, Susan.
‫المعذرة، لكننا سنتأخر يا "سوزان".
Saleed, these two no further.
‫"سليد"، امنع دخول هذين.
Dreams about what? What sorts of dreams?
‫ماذا ترين في أحلامك؟ أحلام من أي نوع؟
Susan, what do you dream about?
‫"سوزان"، ماذا ترين في أحلامك؟
Su-- Do you dream about a girl called Lindy?
‫هل ترين فتاة تُدعى "ليندي"؟
Do you dream about a place called Pacifico del Rio?
‫هل ترين مكانًا يُدعى "باسيفيكو ديل ريو"؟
Do you dream about being an ambulance?
‫هل ترين أنك إسعاف؟
Sorry, I've really got to go.
‫آسفة، عليّ الذهاب.
- Being an ambulance? - She remembered them.
‫- إسعاف؟ ‫- تذكّرت الأحلام.
She doesn't know how, but she remembered them.
‫لا تعرف كيف، لكنها تذكّرت الأحلام.
Increase search parameters.
‫زيادة عوامل البحث.
Morris, try running it backwards.
‫"موريس"، جرّب تشغيلها بشكل عكسي.
Let's see what happens if we reverse time and rewind the VHS.
‫لنر ما سيحدث ‫إن عكسنا الزمن وأعدنا شريط الفيديو للخلف.
- The hell? - Oh, my God.
‫- ما هذا؟ ‫- يا إلهي.
Doctor, are you there?
‫هل تسمعني يا دكتور؟
We found something at the heart of that shape.
‫وجدنا شيئًا في مركز ذلك الشكل.
What is it?
‫ما هو؟
It's the TARDIS.
‫إنه "تارديس".
No, but the TARDIS was there on Ruby Road. We know that.
‫لكن "تارديس" كانت هناك في شارع "روبي". ‫نعرف ذلك.
It's there for a second time. Which you said couldn't happen.
‫إنها هناك لمرة ثانية. ‫وأنت قلت إنه لا يمكن حدوث ذلك.
But this time, it's 20 metres to the north,
‫لكنها 20 مترًا نحو الشمال في هذه المرة،
and that thing is wrapped around it.
‫وذلك الشيء ملتف حولها.
But how?
‫لكن كيف؟
I don't know.
‫لا أعرف.
Doctor, what was that?
‫ما كان ذلك يا دكتور؟
It's made that noise before.
‫أصدرت ذلك الصوت من قبل.
99% and rising.
‫99 بالمئة وترتفع.
Except the trap is here.
‫باستثناء أن الفخ هنا.
I hate to say this, but the shape exists around the TARDIS on the VHS.
‫أكره قول هذا، لكن الشكل موجود ‫حول "تارديس" في شريط الفيديو.
But what if it exists around the TARDIS now,
‫لكن ماذا إن كان يُوجد حول "تارديس" الآن،
and we just can't see it?
‫ولا يمكننا رؤيته؟
Kate, clear the area.
‫أخلي المنطقة يا "كيت".
Evacuate the ops room. Leave the TARDIS alone.
‫أخلي كل غرف العمليات. ‫اتركي "تارديس" وحدها.
O-Okay, I've-I've gotta stay here.
‫حسنًا، عليّ البقاء هنا.
I think Susan Triad is a part of it.
‫أظن أن "سوزان ترياد" جزء من هذا.
Cue laughter.
‫اضحكي.
On my orders, all non-essential staff will clear the room right now.
‫عند أمري، سيخرج كل الموظفين غير الضروريين ‫من القاعة الآن.
All non-essential staff, out!
‫ليخرج كل الموظفين غير الضروريين!
Ruby! Ruby.
‫"روبي"!
I'm sorry. You're part of this.
‫آسفة. أنت جزء من هذا.
I need you to stay, but your mother will be taken home.
‫أريدك أن تبقي، لكن ستُؤخذ أمك إلى المنزل.
- I'm staying with her. Get her out.
‫- أريد البقاء معها. ‫- أخرجها.
- Mum, what do you want me to do? - Come home with me.
‫- أمي، ماذا تريدين أن أفعل؟ ‫- عودي إلى البيت معي.
Then you're not helping.
‫إذًا أنت لا تساعدين.
Which means I love you, thank you and goodbye.
‫ما يعني أنني أُحبك وشكرًا ووداعًا.
This way, ma'am.
‫من هنا يا سيدتي.
The Vlinx, scan the TARDIS.
‫"فلينكس"، افحص "تارديس".
Commence maximum scan.
‫بدء فحص بالحد الأقصى.
Analysis confirms life-form.
‫يؤكد التحليل وجود شكل حياتي.
But we can't see it, but it registers on the quantum search.
‫لكننا لا نراه، لكنه يُرى على البحث الكمي.
Susan. Susan.
‫"سوزان".
- Susan. Susan. Susan. - All right, all right. Thank you!
‫- "سوزان". ‫- حسنًا. شكرًا!
Thank you! We've had our fun.
‫شكرًا! حظينا بالمرح.
- Especially you. Whoo!
‫خاصةً أنت.
But it's my honour to be here today.
‫لكن وجودي هنا اليوم شرف لي.
And my duty.
‫وواجبي.
Because we know what we've done.
‫لأننا نعرف ما فعلناه.
The tech billionaires.
‫مليارديرات التقنية.
We've taken your money...
‫أخذنا أموالكم
- ...while our technology spreads lies,
‫بينما تنشر تقنيتنا الأكاذيب
fraud and riots.
‫والزيف وأعمال الشغب.
But no more.
‫لكن لم يعد الأمر كذلك.
It ends today.
‫سينتهي ذلك اليوم.
Doctor, to confirm, the TARDIS is-- It's surrounded.
‫دكتور، للتأكيد، "تارديس" محاطة.
- It's invisible, but it's a living thing. - ...the hands of the human race. To rebuild.
‫- إنه خفي، لكنه كائن حي. ‫- …أيادي الجنس البشري. لإعادة البناء.
- And I think-- I think we can succeed.
‫- وأظن… ‫- أظن أن بوسعنا النجاح.
Uh, I mean, I hope--
‫أعني أنني آمل…
Doctor, we need you here right now.
‫دكتور، نحتاج إليك هنا حالًا.
- Yes, I know, but-- Sorry.
‫- أجل، أعرف، لكن… ‫- آسفة.
- Doctor. - I know. Wait, wait, wait.
‫- دكتور. ‫- أعرف. انتظري.
Been a hell of a day. - Kate, get Ruby to the Time Window.
‫- كان يومًا شاقًا. ‫- "كيت"، خذي "روبي" إلى النافذة الزمنية.
- What for? - You do not question.
‫- لماذا؟ ‫- لا تسألي.
You move.
‫تحركي.
- Sullivan, take her. And run. - Just go.
‫- خذها يا "سوليفان". وأسرعا. ‫- اذهبي.
I hope...
‫آمل…
I hope. I dare to hope.
‫آمل. أجرؤ على الأمل.
Who was he?
‫من كان؟
But I keep having bad dreams.
‫لكن تراودني كوابيس باستمرار.
Doctor, the scan says this life-form is woven
‫دكتور، يشير الفحص ‫إلى أن الشكل الحياتي مغزول
- into the fabric of the TARDIS itself... - All my ideas come to me in dreams.
‫- في نسيج "تارديس" نفسها… ‫- تأتيني كل أفكاري في أحلام.
...like it's part of it.
‫…كأنه جزء منها.
At arms. With me.
‫أشهروا السلاح. رافقوني.
My name is Kate Lethbridge-Stewart,
‫اسمي "كيت ليثبريدج ستيوارت"،
commander-in-chief of the Unified Intelligence Taskforce,
‫القائدة العامة ‫لـ"فريق الاستخبارات الموحد"،
and I demand that you show yourself.
‫وأطالب بأن تُظهر ذاتك.
He has hidden in the howling void.
‫اختفى في الفراغ المقفز.
- He has hidden within the tempest. - What?
‫- اختفى داخل العاصفة. ‫- ماذا؟
He has braved the storm and the darkness and the pain.
‫واجه العاصفة والظلام والألم.
And he whispered to the vessel.
‫وهمس إلى الآنية.
Who has? Who do you mean?
‫من همس؟ من تقصدين؟
All this time, he whispered and delighted and seduced,
‫طوال هذا الوقت، همس وأسرّ وأغوى،
and the vessel did obey,
‫وأطاعت الآنية،
for none shall be more mighty and none shall be more wise
‫لأنه لن يكون هناك من هو أقوى وأحكم
- than the king himself. - Harriet, what are you doing?
‫- من الملك نفسه. ‫- "هارييت"، ماذا تفعلين؟
And the Lord of Time was blind and vain and knew nothing.
‫وسيد الزمن كان أعمى ومغرورًا ولم يعرف شيئًا.
- What is happening in there? - It's Harriet. It's like...
‫- ماذا يحدث هناك؟ ‫- إنها "هارييت". كأنها…
She's possessed.
‫ممسوسة.
Kate, who is she?
‫"كيت"، من تكون؟
Harriet. You met her. - Yeah, I know. But what is her full name?
‫- "هارييت". قابلتها. ‫- أعرف. لكن ما اسمها بالكامل؟
Harriet. Harriet Arbinger.
‫"هارييت آربنجر".
Harbinger.
‫النذير.
The gods bring harbingers to warn us of their coming.
‫يرسل الآلهة منذرين لإنذارنا بقدومهم.
But which god?
‫لكن أي إله؟
I dream of blue skin.
‫أحلم ببشرة زرقاء.
I dream of metal eyes.
‫أحلم بأعين معدنية.
I don't know what he wanted me to do. Why am I here?
‫لا أعرف ما أرادني أن أفعل. لماذا أنا هنا؟
Time Window closing.
‫النافذة الزمنية تُغلق.
- They said this thing was broken. - It's starting to remember.
‫- قالوا إنها معطلة. ‫- بدأت تتذكر.
It's going back to Christmas Eve.
‫عادت إلى عشية الكريسماس.
I dream of worlds with orange skies.
‫أحلم بعوالم ذات سماوات برتقالية.
You will step away from your desk.
‫ابتعدي عن مكتبك.
Colonel, back away. Stand with me.
‫تراجع أيها العقيد. قف إلى جانبي.
I'm not losing another officer.
‫لن أفقد ضابطًا آخر.
And in-- in every dream, I'm there.
‫أنا هناك في كل حلم.
We know TARDIS is indestructible. - Doctor.
‫- نعرف أن "تارديس" لا يمكن تدميرها. ‫- دكتور.
- If it's hostile, how do we fight it? - There's something wrong.
‫- كيف نحاربها إن كانت عدائية؟ ‫- ثمة خطب.
But who am I?
‫لكن من أكون؟
There is the Toymaker, the god of games.
‫هناك "صانع الألعاب"، إله الألعاب.
There is Trickster, the god of traps.
‫هناك "المخادع"، إله الفخاخ.
There is Maestro, the god of music.
‫هناك "مايسترو"، إله الموسيقى.
- There is Reprobate, the god of spite.
‫هناك "الناقم"، إله الضغينة.
- No! Get away from her! Don't touch her! - There is the Mara, the god of beasts.
‫- لا! ابتعد عنها! لا تلمسها! ‫- هناك "مارا"، إله الوحوش.
And the threefold deity of malice and mischief and misery.
‫والإله الثلاثي، الخبث والضرر والبؤس.
Warning. Manifestation.
‫تحذير. ظهور.
There are gods of skin and shame and secrets.
‫هناك آلهة الجلد والعار والأسرار.
- There is Incensor... - Doctor, she needs you!
‫- هناك "المحرضة"… ‫- دكتور، تحتاج إليك!
...the god of disaster, and her children called Doubt and Dread.
‫…إلهة الكوارث، وطفلاها الشك والفزع.
And standing on high is the mother and father and other of them all.
‫وفوقهم الأم والأب والآخر لهم جميعًا.
Whatever it is, here it comes.
‫أيًا يكن، إنه قادم.
For the god of all gods has returned.
‫لأن إله الآلهة قد عاد.
And his names are many.
‫وأسماؤه كثيرة.
His name has been Set, and Seth, and Setekh.
‫كان اسمه "ست" و"سث" و"ستيخ".
And his one true name forevermore is...
‫واسمه الحقيقي إلى الأبد هو…
Sutekh.
‫"سوتيخ".
It was the wrong anagram.
‫كان ترتيب الحروف الخطأ.
Probable trap. 100%.
‫احتمالية الفخ 100 بالمئة.
Mel, get away from her. Both of you.
‫ابتعدي عنها يا "ميل". ابتعدا.
Don't let her touch you.
‫لا تسمحا لها بلمسكما.
Bailey, get back. Leave her alone.
‫تراجع يا "بايلي". اتركها وشأنها.
You said you were a doctor.
‫قلت إنك دكتور.
- Why don't you try to help?
‫لم لا تحاول مساعدتها؟
Sutekh is the god of death, and by his hand,
‫"سوتيخ" هو إله الموت، وبيده،
all creation shall fall into dust and ashes and ruin.
‫ستتحول الخليقة بأكملها ‫إلى تراب ورماد وخراب.
I bring Sutekh's gift of death.
‫أجلب إليكم هبة الموت من "سوتيخ".
Tell all humanity...
‫أخبروا البشرية بأكملها…
I am Sutekh.
‫أنا "سوتيخ".
The god of death.
‫إله الموت.
I am the night.
‫أنا الليل.
I am the terror.
‫أنا الرعب.
I am the loss.
‫أنا الفقد.
Mum?
‫أمي؟
And all life will perish at my hand.
‫وستفنى كل الحياة بيدي.
Did you think I was family, Doctor?
‫هل حسبتني قريبتك يا دكتور؟
I bring Sutekh's gift of death.
‫أجلب هبة الموت من "سوتيخ".
For you.
‫من أجلك.
And for all in your tiny,
‫ولكل كونك
vile, incessant universe.
‫الضئيل والمنحط والمزعج.